you're listening to revolution radio
freedom slips comm 100%
listener-supported radio and now we
return you to your host
[Music]
well hello and welcome to whistle blower
nation here on revolution radio and I'm
your host Ella thank you for joining me
again this week first off what is a
whistle blower a whistle blow is a
person who makes public disclosures of
wrongdoing corruption and crime these
courageous people often suffer
retaliatory actions because of her
disclosures and I'm here to celebrate
these people and give them a platform
because shining a light on wrongdoing
wherever it occurs plays an important
role in keeping society peaceful free
and just so with me today I have a
returning guest I have kollene
rolly-polly no do we have you there yes
no race I'm going to give you guys a
little bit of background about her she
was here last week as I mentioned and
and we were able to do an hour interview
and we talked a little better background
and some of the some of the
circumstances around her whistleblowing
but this week we're not going to look
more detail about the circumstances that
surrounded the disclosure in the events
around that so first off a little bit
about her again
kollene Raley is a retired FBI special
agent on former Minneapolis division
legal counsel who taught constitutional
law and law enforcement ethics to FBI
agents and other law enforcement then
became a whistleblower about the FBI's
pre 9/11 of failures
testifying to the Joint Intelligence
Committee inquiry the Senate Judiciary
Committee and the inspector general
staff of the Department of Justice
she was named along with two other
corporate whistleblowers as Time People
magazine's Person of the Year in 2002
and she was also on the cover
in early March 2003 she warned FBI
director robert muller of further
problems including his going along with
the Bush administration's deceptive plan
to launch war on what would become the
counter-productive war on Iraq a country
that had nothing to do with the 9/11
attacks sadly enough despite all facts
to the contrary the Bush administration
was able to fool 70% of the American
public into believing that saddam
hussein was behind 9/11 since retiring
from the FBI rally continues to write
and speak out about the perpetual global
war on terror that has exponentially
increased terrorism worldwide and made
the situation far worse i guess you
would agree with that correct colleen
yeah that's that's it in a nutshell and
it's not over where we're heading into
the 17th
year now of perpetual war as well as
reduced civil liberties and really
adherence to the law which there should
be a lot more whistleblowers about
because it just seems to get worse and
worse yeah I definitely and so to go
back a little bit we'll touch upon some
of what we talked about last week you
know you were a legal person in the FBI
and you were an ethics teacher and you
had just given him like a PowerPoint
presentation one way prior to 9/11 and
so ethics to you were the highest of
importance and holding the Constitution
was what you were taught to do and so
then some things were brought to your
attention and can you tell it can you
tell the listeners what happened exactly
well beginning you know this really
wasn't brought to my attention that much
I was aware a little bit of it but
beginning already in spring of 2001 and
throughout the summer of 2001 there was
a lot of intelligence flowing into all
agencies of the intelligence community
not just the FBI of course the CIA and
the NSA had even far more intelligence
that it an attack was going to occur
that they didn't share they did share
everything with the FBI but the FBI also
had its own intelligence coming in and
so there was a lot in if they you know
afterwards that they said if they would
have connected the dots they could have
prevented 9/11 essentially these
officials in all of these agencies were
not reading the intelligence either
we're not reading or after 9/11 they
they they denied having even received
those memos that United even having seen
them or read them or anything they
denied sharing the information with
other agencies with other officials in
the same agency and they didn't act on
the intelligence and so but you would
never have known that after 9/11 of
course they used the shock and awe that
kind of a the trauma of 9/11 was
exploited very opportunistically on
several levels one level was to begin
war
that they had wanted to do these these
Warhawk think tanks neocon think tanks
had been plotting to start war on on the
Mideast essentially but beginning with
Iraq
they've been plotting that for years
before and they said if we got a new
Pearl Harbor well they used 9/11 then as
their new Pearl Harbor Harbor and
there's in the books that have come out
where people have written their
biographies people in the cabinet and
Bush's cabinet they said that even
within days short day after they were
already saying oh now that we had the
attack happened look we can use this to
to gin up war on on Iraq so but that was
just one thing the other thing that was
very serious here and it really deals
with my legal background was that they
basically commissioned John you a junior
attorney in the Office of Legal Counsel
who partnered up with a senior fellow
and they began then to write dozens of
memos that essentially said the
Constitution no longer is in force and
they didn't say it in that in so many
words I'm I'm really kind of uh what's
the word I'm I'm telling you what the
the memo said but you got pages and
pages and pages and they basically were
very what's the word convoluted hard to
read but they said that the Bill of
Rights the the freedom of press freedom
of speech freedom against warrantless
searches not based on probable cause
freedom against self-incrimination ie
torture they they went through the laws
in the series of memos and basically
said now that we're in war we don't have
to follow the Constitution anymore and
again there was a whole series of them
it's not just one were hundreds of pages
and very few people have even read these
at this point the ACLU has looked at
some of them you know some some
attorneys have looked at some of them
but almost nobody has read them all but
they think they constructed a under the
law of war it's you can establish a form
of martial law martial law is a misnomer
it mean
the absence of law it's you know Lincoln
tried to do this in the Civil War way
when he had editors rounded up for
writing things that were critical of the
Union so this happens in wartime and it
began it was one of those opportunistic
things that began right after 9/11 a
whole series of illegal actions and like
I said now were 17 years out right into
our 17th year out from that start and
essentially nothing has been fixed if
anything it's been rubber stamped now by
the Congress and you know the public has
gotten desensitized to almost all of it
we just assume we're going to be in
perpetual war forever and we've and we
like we've been accepting of the fact
that we're going to be under
surveillance Americans will be under
surveillance will have harsh
interrogation tactics and and will
launch wars in foreign countries I mean
all these things that we've just come
now after all these years to accept
little by little it's it's pretty
frustrating you know you know there's a
something said about whistleblowers if
you go back there's that old myth of
Cassandra that she was doomed to keep
warning about really horrible things
that were gonna happen but people would
not pay attention to her and then the
worst would happen that was this old
myth of Cassandra and and you know it's
it's a horrible thing to to warn about
some something that even threatens
Public Safety and then you know have
people all well it does who cares blah
blah blah and then have it happen and
now what can look in the person you know
Warren you can say oh I told you so when
people are you know millions of people
have died that doesn't work and it's
it's just a real sad situation to have
so few of the public
educated enough in understanding of the
framework of the law enough to care and
try to put some pressure on their
elected government in order to return
you know if you use the framework of
9/11 there were the color codes the
green
yellow red and of course they've been
people thought after after a few years I
think it took about six seven eight
years before someone said well that's
kindergarten to say we're in yellow were
in yellow alert or orange alert or red
alert you know red alert by the way is
Armageddon so they said well that
doesn't make any sense and by the way we
can never go back to green Green was
normal you know Green was considered to
be normal
I think that's we do have to try to get
back to what we had where we had a
government that was at least trying to
follow the law and that was you know not
doing these terrible things but it's
very very difficult right now because
people are afraid and they'll believe
anything yeah and then do you mind going
back into your particular story cuz I
want to hear about your memo and I know
you were up all night and you were gonna
go the next day and share it can you
maybe expound upon that and I'd love to
hear about it and you know I want to
keep this about you and what you
actually it so I would love that
well if anyone is really interested in
this history of on 9/11 there's a site
on the web called history Commons it's
kind of like Wikipedia and if you put in
Mousawi history Commons you will find
pages and pages and the the factual
statements are just like Wikipedia
they're all footnoted and linked to
whatever news article or authority and
so maybe not all of it is correct of
course because it will depend upon the
underlying news report that was the the
source of authority for that statement
but I just happened to review that the
other day and over time when they first
started history Commons it wasn't that
accurate because it's like Wikipedia
when wikipedia thing just starts heaven
knows if it's accurate but over time
public source
you know people open source works
because people go in there and correct
this and correct that and so if you're
really interested in the history of the
terrorist suspect that was detected in
Minnesota in August of two
you should read that whole long pages of
Mousawi on history Commons it's quite
accurate and even I was shocked to see
how much information later was was
discovered that of moussaoui's different
earlier terrorist actions in Europe and
in Chechnya and whatever but but in
August there is a there are two calls
that come from whistleblower flight
engineers and flight instructors in a
flight school in Eagan Minnesota and
these two flight engineer instructors do
not even know they were calling there
were whistleblowers because their bosses
told them to keep quiet about it and so
they both call the FBI two different
places and they say we've got this
unbelievably most suspicious a student
we've ever seen and we think he could be
you know planning some kind of terrorist
attack whatever one of our agents then
who it really was probably the best
agent equipped in the office to follow
up on that lead because he himself had
been in navy intelligence and he had
been I think he was either a flight what
do you call it a pilot or else a flight
person that helped son Navy Navy flights
he's the person that engine you know
that locates or whatever but he was an
agent and that very day within hours he
and another I NS agent went out to
interview Mousawi who was this Moroccan
French Moroccan flight student in Eagan
and they interviewed him they were first
by the way they interviewed his own
flight instructor who also said oh yes
he's the most suspicious student we've
ever had and gave those agents literally
pages of facts about why he was
suspicious
the agents went back to the office oh I
should back up they took Mousawi into
custody after interviewing him because
they were so afraid that he was in the
midst of planning a terrorist attack and
be also because his visa had lapsed so
they
took him into custody along with his
personal effects and laptop I&S dead by
the way because of his visa then the
agents put Dahl all those facts down
into an emergency request for a FISA
this is ironic because now today there's
a memo released by the Republicans
staffers about all of the irregularities
and false information that went into the
FISA application for one of the Trump
campaign volunteers and of course that's
created huge news that this that the FBI
misled the FISA Court on its
surveillance of Carter page one of the
Trump campaign people calling him a
Russian spy all based on specious what
they called the dossier etc so that's
all over the news
our agents back in two thousand of 2001
requested an emergency FISA on Mousawi
so that they could search his personal
effects and laptop and they are
headquarters and then also they sent out
leads to France and the United Kingdom
and so they did all this very quickly
and what happened was our headquarters
then over the course of a few days
basically blocked that request from
going to the Department of Justice even
from from even going to their superiors
inside the FBI
they didn't even they took it up one
level but they did not take it up any
further than one level and they didn't
take it over course to the Department of
Justice and certainly not to the FISA
Court and so our agents were pulling
their hair out in August trying to think
of any of all kinds of other ways they
called to the CIA in the meantime this
this info that they had gotten initially
was briefed to George Tenet who was the
director of Central Intelligence
he got briefed already on August 23rd
and was briefed I think more than once
and no one knows if he briefed the
president and about it or not but we
know that Kennedy himself knew can it a
people didn't understand this because
they thought no one was in charge
of the 16 intelligence agencies and
that's why they all had to have created
a new office of director of intelligence
afterwards that was a lie they they
already had somebody in charge it was
the director of Central Intelligence
which was George Tenet
and he didn't want to take
responsibility so they made it seem like
there was no one in charge but he was he
received this information on August 23rd
there was all kinds of things like that
that were being covered up after 9/11
and they covered up the Phoenix memo
they covered up all these part of the
problem for the FBI was the CIA had not
shared critical intelligence about a
meeting that had been monitored by the
CIA like two years before in Kuala
Lumpur and two of the people act that
al-qaeda meeting in Kuala Lumpur came to
California and they they turned out to
be the pilot hijackers they were part of
the group the group of terrorists
hijackers but the CIA never told the FBI
so there were all these things that were
being covered up and still to this day
even though my memo did lead to a
Inspector General report if you read the
9/11 Commission you'll see sites to the
inspector general report I think some of
it is also on the history Commons
history common sight and so some of the
information eventually it took a long
time couple of years even for you know
some of the information to come out but
to this day there's been cover-up of a
lot just last year they finally
uncovered 28 pages that they had blocked
which showed that Saudi Arabia which
should have been no surprise because 15
of the 19 hijackers were from Saudi
Arabia but there was a lot of
investigation that showed Saudi Arabian
officials had helped or some in some
ways aided the hijackers and that was
covered up until last year it's pretty
incredible
or in all these wars with countries that
had nothing to do with 9/11 and to this
day our intelligence people have covered
up a lot of the truth about 9/11 that if
we know all those things they could have
been fixed an easy fix for instance to
some of the problems of not reading and
not reading the your memos that come to
you not sharing the information well
that but that kind of stuff is a lot
more easily fixed you can put in
accountability mechanisms to ensure that
people read what when their name is on
it they basically have to have some way
of initialing off to show that they've
read it and then of course if afterwards
something bad happens that person is not
able to deny that they ever that they
did see that memo so that's a very
simple thing to fix very simple to fix a
major problem people denying that they
got memos very easy to fix
also the sharing of info that's easy to
fix a lot easier than killing millions
of people in countries that we that had
nothing to do with the 9/11 hijackers
and in fact covering up the country they
did have something to do with it so it's
it's a it's a mess you know if we were
from another planet and we were looking
down on this you would just have your
your mouth would be open because you
wouldn't believe that you could do these
things but because we're all part of
this partisan blind loyalty you know
kind of this this manipulation that goes
on from the politicians on down of both
parties we're really in the dark to a
large extent theme Americans really have
not ever figured out that they've been
bamboozled for a long time and it's it's
a sad and dangerous extremely dangerous
moment that we're living through now you
know it seems to be so but I was reading
some of your previous interviews and in
2008 you stated that you had taken a
copy of a bombshell memo to the media
that have probably saved your job can
you elaborate on this a little bit lab
right on this a little bit yeah I did
not take it to the media um so I don't
know what yes
not exactly true but when eight months
after 9/11 when the Joint Intelligence
Committee was finally convening they had
I don't know 30 staffers that they
divvied up and assigned to FBI CIA NSA
and others
I think FAA maybe so they had different
investigators that they are staffers
that they assigned so the FBI had five
or six that just dealt with FBI problems
and then they had some with NSA that
started eight months eight and a half
months eight well no it started before
that started about six months seven
months after 9/11 but it really got
going where I got a call eight months
later and so I had to go to Washington
DC and because I was afraid that I would
forget some of these details because
again it's kind of it's a complicated
thing
I started jotting them down because I
said you know when you're talking to
somebody you know you always leave
things out and I said you know I want to
be very complete and tell everything I
knew about this Mousawi case I didn't
know very much by the way when you look
at the whole scheme vast amount of stuff
out there the Mousawi is just a small
portion of it so and I only knew about
the most solid case but I'm still I
wanted to jot it down but as I jotted it
down I had about a three-day leap lead
time before I had to go to DC I started
to write it into more of a memo form and
I finally decided that I would take this
memo directly not to the media but
directly to the members of the Joint
Intelligence Committee and anything yeah
and you know stretchers Shelby and Diane
Feinstein is that correct
that's right they weren't the heads
Diane Feinstein later became a head of
the committee but at the time she was
just a member and the reason I I I got
their names from a newspaper article
where I saw that they were asking
questions that we actually were a little
more astute questions then that most by
the way most of Congress didn't even
know any
this at the time they were in the dark
completely in the dark and so their
questions of the of the FBI director for
instance didn't even make sense because
they didn't know any of this so they're
asking questions that were just out in
left-field well I saw a cup with one
bite Feinstein and Shelby that you know
they were a little bit more you know
getting closer to the truth I thought so
I put their names on one was a
Republican and one was a Democrat and
the reason I thought I would take the
memo directly to them was that I thought
there was maybe a possibility that the
staff itself hired by again this Joint
Intelligence Committee staff was being
guided by some retired officials that
had themselves been accused in Prior
inquiries one was a retired FBI attorney
who had been accused of withholding
information from the John Danforth
inquiry of Waco you know what they start
what you start talking about this it is
a real twisted thing because these
agencies always want to put the best
face on bureaucrats careerists want to
put the best spin on really sad you know
terrible mistakes that have occurred in
the past and rather than just blurt out
the truth and say we're sorry this went
wrong whatever they almost always tried
to put the best spin on it and so this
this our former FBI attorney had been
accused of not you know telling the full
truth to the Danforth that inquiry I
actually knew him a little bit and I
thought to myself that it probably
wasn't true exactly I didn't really
believe that he had withheld information
but I thought there was enough chance
that he you know could still you know he
had the power to anything I sit in that
interview didn't have to go any further
and so I thought well I'll just make
sure that this memo then I'll put it in
a memo form and I'll make sure it goes
directly to they probably won't read it
I actually did not even have hopes that
the Senators would read it I had it in
an envelope that said confidential and I
took it to their office in the Senate
heart building kind of a kind of a funny
story because when I got done being
debriefed by the by the Senate excuse me
the joint intelligence committee
staffers which took place in FBI space
and we were minded you could really
speak freely because I had FBI officials
listening in to everything I said to
those staffers and and they could even
stop me from talking if they wanted to
they didn't but they could have they
were mine they call it minding your
being minded when you talk and this is
even to Congress this is this is what I
don't think the American public
understand maybe they do now with this
kind of real partisan wrangling and
that's going on but this has always been
the case secrecy is power and so you
know people don't want the truth to come
out and they will do everything they can
anyways at the end of about to our
interview where I told them you know
most of what I remembered the they said
to me is there anything you know have
you left anything out is there anything
that you I want to make sure we know and
I said well if there is anything I left
out it's in this memo and then I pulled
out this this 1213 page memo that I had
written and as I handed in the memo they
kind of looked at me like whoa and I
walked out and so I gave him this memo
and then I I took a copy of the memo to
the director FBI director's office
because of course he's the the buck
stops here and he's the firt it was
directed it was directed addressed to
the director it these offices are hard
to find in the FBI because it's a real
the J Edgar Hoover Building is just as
tangled hallways and it's very hard to
find things yeah it's just they have
color lines on the hallways so people
you're supposed to follow these color
lines to go oh my gosh it's like a mess
Jagger Hoover was kind of a say a sadist
because he doesn't have MIT there's no
windows in that building and it's just
like a tunnels it's almost like tunnels
it's a mess all right so
so I found the directors office then I
also took a copy to the Office of
Professional Responsibility
which is the internal affairs for the
FBI so that they could you know see if
they wanted to investigate this and then
I got a cab and I went to the Senate
heart building at the time the Senate
heart building you couldn't get into it
it was a huge long line because the
anthrax letters had been sent to the
Senate building and people had been
exposed to anthrax and so they had top
security and you couldn't really get
into the Senate heart building so I I
talked to a security guard and I said I
showed him my credentials and I said I
have to get to two Senate offices with
this confidential memo and so that guard
escorted me to both of those offices and
I you know left a copy not even hope
just hoping that they might read it and
basically be able to finally at least
ask some more intelligent questions
because they were didn't even understand
what had happened and this is again
eight-and-a-half months later they
really really had no idea so after I
left those I caught a I caught a plane
right back I took the cab to the airport
and flew back here and in about two days
later is when someone from the probably
someone in Congress I don't know staffer
somebody must have then called CNN New
York Times and said you know there's
there's a lot more to a lot more to 9/11
here we got this memo and that's when it
started to leak I see and then what
happened then were people inviting
anyone to interview at that point cuz I
know you did some fairly large
interviews well yeah there are a lot of
there was a media short you know
wherever they want to call it a media
frenzy for a couple weeks I had the Time
magazine photographer and reporter down
in my driveway they didn't even leave at
night they were hoping to like take a
picture you know of me
and out of my driveway my house has a
back way in and so I went up the back
way and he never kind of basically
cheated them out of a picture and stuff
they had they found an old picture that
they put on their magazine just from
their old footage of something because I
didn't even stop to get a picture and
then they yeah New York Times called and
other other reporters were calling me at
the time and I didn't really talk to any
of them they the memo within gosh
another day or two maybe the day or two
after the media heard about it they
didn't actually have the copy and so the
FBI
maybe DOJ tried to keep it from leaking
further by classifying it secret and
they they've used a pretext of like one
word and the memo the word French was
classified so they used that as a
pretext to classify it to try to keep it
from leaking but in fact Time magazine
and some others within a couple of days
got the entire memo and then yeah for
for a little while there was a bit of a
media frenzy and I didn't really I
didn't really talk to the media at all I
got called within another couple of days
by senators Leahy and Grassley who were
the heads of the Senate Judiciary
Committee because of course they have
oversight over the FBI and if in all of
these things you know dealt with their
their role as as trying to conduct
oversight the the Senate Judiciary was
conducting its own investigation of 9/11
and then I also got called by the two
minnesota senators i don't know if i got
called by them because i don't remember
talking to either one of them but they
at the time was Wellstone and Mark
Dayton where the two minnesota senators
and what they did all four of them wrote
letters to the Attorney General and to
the
hi director asking that I not be fired
and the combination of four senators
letters that I not be fired worked and
Muller said pretty quickly that no she
won't be fired Ashcroft was a little
more cagey about it and he didn't really
he didn't really promise I wouldn't be
fired he kind of you know just was gave
a vague answer back but the agents
association knew just you know because
this wasn't about me personally this was
about the agents in the office that our
office had been you know sorted by
headquarters and so the agents
association obviously took the side of
the agents that had been you know that
there should have been respected and
they should have their information was
credible etc etc so that that
whistleblowing
did not stand me in good stead with
headquarters personnel they were very
angry about it and and the other group
that was angry were the retired agents
retired agents were under the old Hoover
rule that no one speaks out of school
so-called no never embarrassed the
bureau was Hoover's rule and so you can
never ever tell the truth about anything
that had happened that was illegal or
wrong or or public safety issue you know
Hoover would you know would not like it
and so that old rule you know some
agents were still in that mode and they
you know wrote me some letter saying you
know you should there's a old loyalty
hmm there's an old loyalty poem that
Hoover had this was before my day
because Hoover died in 72 and I did not
join the FBI until early of early
nineteen eighty one so you know and but
in the years that Hoover ruled he had
this old I think its Elliott Hubbard
poem about blind loyalty and I used to
be able to recite it I don't know if I
can right now I've forgotten some of it
but it's if you you you can never
criticize the organization if you work
for it there starts this way if you work
for a man then you know keep your mouth
shut and never criticize because if you
do the first high wind that comes along
will blow you away
and you may never know why it that you
can google it it's Elliott Hubbard poem
and the title is loyalty and for Hoover
blind loyalty was the top virtue and so
if oil T is the top virtue then then
integrity is you know way at the bottom
you know that's it that's a that's a
lesser thing and a lot of people still
have that ethic they think loyalty
matters more than than integrity and
truth yeah we'd have a perfect world if
integrity was the number one priority in
my opinion it just but you know
integrity just you you really do I think
in this day and age you know especially
there's so much information out there
and if you have it and it's something
that needs to be disclosed I encourage
people to do so I mean you'll still you
know I know there's always backlash and
I guess that's I wanted to see if you
were affected in any other way as well
because we know there's backlash from
sometimes speaking out and you've kind
of indicated a little bit like people
unhappy at the bureau in certain
departments but you know you know you
were regarded as a hero it seems to be
and I one of the things to kind of go
off in different topic I said like I
believe that the landscape of
whistleblowing has changed dramatically
over the years but it you may have a
different opinion you know what your
experience was but in - mm - you were
kind of allowed it as a hero for
whistleblowing and in the past few years
whistleblowers seem to have been
targeted smeared blacklisted and been
potentially murdered and put in prison
so it has definitely been a big change
in attitude and maybe a little bit down
the road when we're speaking here you
can kind of tell me why you think that
is and what has occurred in your opinion
that's kind of created that shift yeah I
I think that that Time magazine of 2002
which was called the whistleblowers
they're the persons of the year were the
whistleblower
I went a long way towards making people
think that it was good and right to tell
the truth it was it wasn't just the FBI
case that was an run and worldcom these
big corporations where everybody went up
goes along with the lies from the top on
down until the whole thing crumbles and
there and all the shareholders and all
the employees and investors and everyone
loses everything right
those big debacles are lessons and so
for a short while at this this moment in
2002 the mainstream media and the
publican and you know people and power
weren't necessarily cool with it all but
but but a lot of people understood the
need for truth-telling I always thought
it was funny that people weren't more
understanding of the need for truth
helling because in the FBI as the
investigators of for instance corporate
fraud healthcare fraud you know even
defense military fraud I mean all the
frauds that the FBI would investigate
over the years guess what required
there's no way the FBI knows these
things they will never be able to figure
out a Bernie Madoff 10-15 years they'll
never be able to figure that out on
their own they absolutely require a
whistleblower to come in write them a
letter and say you know I want to get
this off my chest
I've been the bookkeeper for Bernie
Madoff and he has cheating lots of
people you know it requires that kind of
whistleblowing and so in the in the FBI
like I worked on mafia and mob stuff in
New York City and the only way that we
could make an inroad into the organized
crime was if we got information from you
maybe not a whistleblower you know could
be an informant or our cooperating
witnesses they're all the same by the
way these are all interchangeable except
that in some cases informants have their
own incentives etc but and so you have
to be aware of different motivations and
things but but the if you get you have
to have
that information from somebody that
tells you the truth and so it's pretty
odd that an agency that recruits and who
and encourages whistleblowing and
encourages people in the public to tell
the truth about stuff would then turn
and say but we don't want to know
anything about ourselves I guess it
isn't so incredible but this is people
will like it if it's if it's the airing
the dirty laundry of somebody else
they'll be fine but if it's there
themselves their own institution and
this can be everything from the Catholic
the Catholic hierarchy you know it's
it's good otherwise good people get
locked into this groupthink
in blind loyalty of their own group and
they think that their goals and their
mission of their entity is more
important than the ways in the process
it's always ends justify the means you
know the the people who are covering up
for the pedophile priests thought well
our religion is more important
maintaining people's faith and trust in
Catholicism is more important than
telling the truth about these pedophile
priests and so people are always doing
this they're making an ends justify the
means especially the people who are in
power in these in these various groups
and and what happened is after this 2002
moment passed for instance in my own
case I didn't stop of course things got
worse after 9/11 they used the
exploitation of it was even worse than
the failure to that allowed it to happen
the there were 3,000 people that died on
9/11 you know how many people have died
since millions of people have died it's
horrible and so this thing just got
worse and worse and nobody opened their
mouth about any of that there was there
was a roundup of innocent people in in
New York City after 9/11 and everybody
kept their mouth shut for a couple of
years about that they started to torture
take people to black sites Muller Muller
at the top of the FBI who now has
considered this pinnacle of
Eggar t he never made a report that he
knew of that people were being tortured
that's completely violates both domestic
constitutional and an international law
to torture and Mahler you know he just
swept it under the rug he told us a
person you're the second person he was
kind of at your caliber who's mentioned
molar is how he chooses his integrity
and the best bit in the best and I hate
to say that because I do like him but
you're the second person who's mentioned
something very similar he uses it
depends as long as it's not gonna affect
him there you go that's exactly I wrote
an article about Muller and call me both
of them because they got this reputation
now because of the partisanship on the
on the liberal side and it's really
hypocritical because the Liberals we're
always criticizing the FBI and the CIA
but now they thought think that these
leaders who by the way worked under the
Bush administration and in really signed
off on all kinds of highly illegal
things but but you know they're very
careful they're very good politicians
and they know how to pick and choose
what will make their reputations
you know burnish their own reputations
and in fact if you really look at the
facts of Muller and Comey they are
involved in all kinds of different the
same you know line of scandals the
anthrax the the targeting of the wrong
person in the anthrax case that they
ended up having to pay five million
dollars to Muller goes all the way back
to the Whitey Bulger cover-up in Boston
where the FBI was operating this
murderous Irish mobster for 20 years and
in Muller probably knew about it he had
a role in that
anyways I I wrote a whole memo detailing
some of these factual things about
Muller and Comey some of the problem is
that leaders who rise up to these
positions have learned the art of
compromise they've learned the art of
almost kind of manipulation etc because
that's what
into their leadership and a lot of
people just fall for it they they want
to believe so hard and in a you know
their group their groups leader that
they they don't really are not objective
it's almost reminds me of Billy Graham
you know you know how Billy Graham could
get all those people to believe that he
was healing them and you know thousands
or thousands of people all Roberts
there's been a whole bunch of these
because the people in the group are so
inclined to want to believe their faith
their blind faith they were so inclined
to put their trust in this person at the
top and that was with this the case with
J Edgar Hoover but it's also the case
with Mahler and call me and and he'd
before them Louie free and a whole and
the press sometimes presidents depending
on on your partisanship whether it's
Clinton or whether it's George Bush it's
it's very strange now that some of our
George Bush for instance who really
started all of this no post 9/11 stuff
is now being lauded as a good guy by
liberals you'll see here interviews now
and there's even a book out that I saw
an interview on NPR where he's being
touted as this great guy and of course
oh you're so much better than Trump and
all the rest and that's that's nonsense
he's one of the people who started this
he fueled terrorism it's it's it's
incredible how little critical thinking
there is in the public and again it's
frustrating to have been a whistleblower
and to have seen how this is all one
thing's led to another and then of
course they have children and
grandchildren who are facing the
consequences of this this really very
dangerous stuff that has occurred you
know increasing terrorism and
confronting nuclear-armed countries now
and it's just really scary yeah it seems
to be so we have about less than 10
minutes so kind of like going on to
about what you're doing today and also
maybe go in into I know that you ran for
office and you didn't succeed but is
there plans to maybe run again
and in what capacity when I retired from
the FBI I initially thought I would you
know I was only 50 and the one of the
remedies from the 9/11 Commission report
three of their 40 recommendations were
to create a civil liberties oversight
board so this is all before anyone knew
Snowden or NSA whistleblowers no one
knew all of them they didn't even know
about torture in in 2004 the 9/11
Commission the 9/11 Commission by the
way some of them knew about torture so
they had recommended that a privacy and
civil liberties oversight board be
formed and I thought well that's great
I'll get on that that will be a way that
I can really contribute here you know
basically not only on my legal
background but you know I thought I
could do something and I actually was
able to get I think eight of our 10
Minnesota Congress persons to recommend
me to Bush at the time to be a member of
that and Bush though did not want to he
did not want to have any oversight of
course no oversight at all over what was
going on so he made sure that the
privacy and civil liberties oversight
board was under him in the White House
and he dragged his feet but eventually
there were four Republicans and one
Democrat put on this board and after a
year or two not very long
the I think the Democrat wrote a report
saying you know we're being thorton we
can't do anything we're not being
allowed you know work we're completely
being restricted and he said I resigned
and so that that and they didn't have
subpoena power or anything so it went
into limbo for several until Obama got
in and when it all excuse me went into
limbo until the Congress changed its a
majority to two Democrat and when that
happened they actually passed an
independent private
cien civil liberties oversight board and
in the meantime I had run for Congress
as a Democrat in Minnesota and lost and
so when they reconsidered this privacy
and civil liberties oversight board I
again went to all of ours you know
Congress person's here and I with the
exception of one that was a Republican
who of course said oh you are a Democrat
I can't support you but the rest of them
I still got five or six to support me in
a bid to be named Obama though however
even though this this board was
reconstituted he didn't want it either
you know the the notion that one one
party is better than the other is
completely nonsense my experience is
that the the power is making these
people it's not the opposite and so he
did the same thing he drugged his feet
it took years and years and finally of
course I was not once elected he finally
got it
he finally had five people on this board
they did not have their first meeting
until after the Snowden disclosures that
was the first time from like 2004 when
the law passed until about 2013 or so I
think it was I don't exactly remember
when they had the first meeting it was a
lot years and years and years from a
recommendation of the 9/11 Commission
and it that's a pretty good interesting
point just to compare with how quickly
the Bush administration said we gotta go
to war in Iraq we got a torture all
those things happen within days after
9/11 the the one fix that would have
made sense which was oversight over this
our to control illegal stuff that was
going on took years and years and years
to get into place but that's what I
really wanted to do I was never picked
for it and running for Congress the only
good thing about it I used to just say
it was like a march into hell for a
heavenly cause because you really see
how corrupt the whole electoral process
is people know Bernie Sanders complained
you know the the Sanders supporters
complain the system
was rigged and Donna Brazile has written
a whole book about some of these highly
irregular funding but the but it it even
before citizens united because I ran in
2005 to 2006 it was already really
corrupt the big money there is no way a
normal good person who does not want to
sell their soul actually in the first
week it to get these millions of dollars
that are required even for a
congressional race it's a minimum of of
at least two to three million dollars
for just a congressional race for a
Senate race it's somewhere around 20
million dollars so unless you're an
independently wealthy you know if you're
if you're you know Bill Gates or
somebody like that or obviously Trump
says thought City had money but if you
have to be independently wealthy or you
have to be willing essentially to sell
your soul I think if the public was more
knowledgeable about the process the
electoral process they would have the
stars in their eyes that they have and
they would be more they would be more
capable of judging these these Congress
persons and Senators because really they
have to sign off on things especially to
these the defense industry to you know
obviously to the to the gun and the
weapons industry but to of the American
Israeli public affairs committee all of
these huge special interests now these
big funders that pick that essentially
they are picking the candidates the
people are not picking them big money is
picking the candidates so it's
impossible to run unless I always told
people if I won the lottery or something
I would I would definitely think about
how did if I had if I had several
million dollars but I can't you can't do
it on your own absolutely impossible
Joe democracy okay well that's good
information and what about advice for
other whistleblowers advice for them
I'm the best there is one way that is
more likely to get a result and
and you have a better chance it's the
queen time process it does you have to
fulfill some requirements there has to
be a false statement in like a grant you
know where it's a tax money that is
funding a national grant let's say
healthcare for instance if you knew or
know about a doctor who's fudging their
their scientific results and they are
getting a federal grant and it goes back
to the False Claims Act in the Civil War
because in in during times of war
there's a lot of defense contractor
fraud so let's say you were making
toilet seats for them for the Pentagon
and you found out that they were
overcharging $1,000 per toiler $10,000
per toilet seat if you knew that you
could file a qui tam lawsuit under seal
and and you would be the whistleblower
and then the the Department of Justice
has a chance to review those lawsuits in
some cases they may actually take your
side by the way it's a small percentage
of cases the same question so I but it's
really important to reiterate that did
you need links or anything you would
like to anything you want to share with
the public you know I've written two
articles one is on the intelligence
ethics issue and it's on the war on
terror if they put in Coleen Rowley the
false promise of the war on terror I
think is the title that's one of my
better articles and the other one is
WikiLeaks in 911 what gangs there we go
and you know what you mentioned torture
earlier so that's a great segue to
introduce my next guess I have the John
Kerry aku and a man the highest
character has served jail because he
refused to participate toward her so
we'll be back after this break guys
[Music]
Thank You Colleen okay bye
good luck Ella thanks so much thank you
hello and welcome back to whistle blower
nation here in revolution radio again
i'm your host ella and who I have with
me now is John Kerry aku do I have you
on the line John oh you sure do oh great
so everything went on hands great to
hear so I'm gonna give them a little bit
a little bio about you I'm gonna start
with one of your quotes there are some
things we should not do even the name of
national security I really like that
quote that is your quote correct yes
ma'am you never know so much so what
John is a former CIA analyst and case
officer a former senior investigator for
the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
and former counterterrorism consultant
while employed by the CIA he was
involved in critical counterterrorism
missions following the terrorist attacks
of September 11th in 2001 but refused to
be trained in so-called enhanced
interrogation techniques and John never
authorized or engaged in these
techniques after leaving the CIA he
appeared on ABC news in an interview
with Brian Ross and during which he
became the first former CIA officer to
confirm that the agency waterboarded
detainees and label waterboarding is
torture and Kuryakin interview revealed
that this practice was not just the
result of a few rogue agents but this
was official US policy approved by the
highest levels of government and the
government started investigating John
immediately after his media appearance
five years later the government finally
succeeded in piecing together enough
information to criminally prosecute him
he became the SEC's whistleblower
indicted by the Obama administration
under the Espionage Act a law designed
to punish spies by the way not
whistleblowers and so John is the sole
CIA agent to go to jail in connection
with the u.s. torture program despite
the fact that he never tortured anyone
rather he blew the whistle nasur rific
wrongdoing so what a pleasure to finally
have this opportunity to interview you
oh thanks for having me
okay so as you know I mentioned to you
this is kind of a tribute to you so you
we have close to an hour so maybe if you
want to add a little bit to that like
share a little bit about your background
if you like and and your educational
background and maybe your life before
serving our countries sure I was born
and raised in western Pennsylvania a
small town in in a rural part of the
state about an hour north of Pittsburgh
and I left just as I was turning 18 to
go to college at George Washington
University here in Washington I got a
bachelor's degree in Middle Eastern
Studies and then I was working on a
master's degree in legislative affairs
it was just before I finished my
master's that that I was recruited into
the CIA by one of my grad school
advisors who was actually undercover as
a grad school adviser he was really a
CIA officer acting as what used to be
called a spotter looking for grad
students who might be a good fit in the
CIA's culture so after I graduated with
my masters I joined the CIA and started
working as an analyst I spent my first
eight years as an analyst working on
Iraq and served overseas a couple of
times in the Middle East I was in
headquarters by 1998 and I switched to
counterterrorism operations went through
the operational training went back
overseas again after the September 11th
attacks I became the CIA's chief of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
and and led a series of raids one night
in March of 2002 that resulted in the
capture of Abu Zubaydah who we believed
at the time was the number three in
al-qaeda that was incorrect but we
believed he was the number three and we
caught I'm not allowed to say the number
but we caught many dozens of additional
al-qaeda fighters that night
I returned to headquarters by the end of
May 2002 and as you noted in your
introduction I was asked if I wanted to
be trained in what they called the use
of enhanced interrogation techniques it
was a torture program I
so at the time I declined I'm sorry to
say that of the 14 people that they
asked to be trained I was the only one
who said no and and I'm glad I did
I have no regrets I left the CIA in 2004
and went into the private sector and
then in 2007 I gave that interview to
Brian Ross at ABC News in which I blew
the whistle on the torture program so
it's been an odyssey really since 2007 I
was investigated for a total of four
years by the FBI but it wasn't the Bush
administration that went after me
it was the Obama administration and I
gave the I gave the interview as I said
in December of 2007 the FBI investigated
me from December o 7 to December 8 and
then closed the case and sent my
attorneys a declination letter declining
to prosecute they concluded that I had
not committed a crime
a month later Barack Obama was
inaugurated and the CIA asked Eric
Holder to secretly reopen the case
against me which he did I had no idea I
was still under investigation and for
the next three years they tapped my
phones they intercepted my emails they
had surveillance teams on me and then
finally in January of 2012 I was charged
with five felonies coming out of that
interview including three counts of
espionage what was going on through in
your head when you heard that when you
heard that sentence what were you
thinking oh that I would jump in front
of a subway train ah I can't I mean I'd
plant plain and plain and simple yeah I
how do you come through something like
that I was I was facing 45 years in
prison I knew in my heart I hadn't done
anything wrong espionage that was that
was ridiculous on its face and by the
end of the year those charges were
thrown out but it becomes an economic
decision I'm glad we have we have some
time I'll explain how this how this all
played out in my attorneys
first conversation with the Justice
Department they made an offer and they
said take a plea to an espionage charge
and you do 10 years and I said I'm not
gonna do 10 minutes I had I've not done
anything wrong
well what the government normally does
if you turn down that first offer
they'll come back with an offer of of 12
years and then 15 years but when they
came back with their second offer with
me it was 8 and then the third offer was
five and one of my attorney said I've
been an attorney for 40 years and I've
never seen them do this before and I
said well why are they coming down in
time and he said because they have no
case and they know they have no case so
finally they came down to three and a
half and they said best and final offer
and I decided to to turn it down and so
they they said that if we were to go to
trial they would seek 45 years which was
a death penalty I'm 53 years old I was I
was 40 48 at the time it's the death
penalty and and I knew from a study that
was released right around that same time
by ProPublica that the government wins
ninety eight point two percent of their
cases and besides that I had hired OJ
Simpson's jury consultant he happens to
be the uncle of my best friend's wife
and he volunteered his very very
expensive services so he flew up he flew
up from Dallas and and he got a security
clearance from the Justice Department
and we went over the entire case and
finally he said to me look if we were in
any other district in America I would
say let's go for it
we're gonna win this thing but you're in
the Eastern District of Virginia they
call it the espionage Court because no
national security defendant has ever won
a case there he said they would convict
a bologna sandwich if the government
asked them to he said look at what your
jury is going to be your jury is going
to be
CIA FBI NSA Homeland Security Pentagon
intelligence community contractors and
their family members you don't stand a
chance take the deal and so we went back
to the Justice Department and we
proposed a year they came back with two
and a half and we decided to cut our
losses you know one of my attorneys said
to me because I was gonna I was gonna
turn down the two-and-a-half and he said
you just don't understand you think this
is about justice and it's not it's about
cutting your losses and finally another
one said if you were my brother I would
beg you to take this deal he said this
can be a blip in your life or it can be
the defining event of your life make it
the blip and so I took the deal and and
I guess you know then you went into the
system and how did you cope what was it
like was it different than you expected
and where there was an opportunity to
just spend time to educate yourself and
really I'm sure someone sitting in and
if in the system like that that gives
you an opportunity to start doing
research you know yeah yes and no yes
and no you're not allowed any computer
access so research is difficult but
here's how how this worked my attorneys
asked the judge to send me to a
minimum-security work camp now in a work
camp there are no bars on the windows
the doors are not locked you're free to
come and go as you please you're on your
honor not to abscond and most people
work in town at a local university or
whatever and minimum security camps are
generally attached to high security or
higher security prisons so the the
prosecution had no objection and the
judge ordered that I be sent to a
minimum security camp so I was assigned
to the prison camp at Loreto
Pennsylvania and I turned myself in on
February 28 to
13 I drove up to the up to the prison
and you just you literally knock on the
door and say I'm John Kiriakou I'm here
to turn myself in and so they put you
through the metal detector and then the
corrections officer began began to lead
me around to the back of the actual
prison and I said no no I'm supposed to
be at the camp across the street and he
laughed and he said not according to my
paperwork you're not so I told myself
take it easy
there's nothing you can do if you flip
out they're gonna put you in solitary so
I just remained silent right and to tell
you the truth I was probably in shock
too so I was processed and it took me
five days to get access to a telephone
and when I finally did I called my lead
attorney and I said hey they put me in
the actual prison with the pedophiles
and the murderers and the drug kingpins
so what do I do and he said oh my god
well we could file a motion but it'll be
two years before we get a hearing and
you'll be home by then I'm sorry buddy
you're gonna have to tough it out and so
I decided that day that I would rely on
my CIA training to make sure that I
remained safe and at the top of the
social heap and what I ended up doing I
ended up writing a book and I won one of
the country's four top literary prizes
for this book I won the pen First
Amendment award and I called the book
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison the
Patriot Act how it's supposed to be for
spies and yes exactly and so I wrote
down these 20 life lessons that the CIA
taught me and I showed how I used each
one of these to stay safe right well
that's great
and so that worked out for you and to
time go did it go fairly quickly once
you were there and you really you don't
it did once you get into the routine it
goes very quickly in the beginning well
you know what I was walking around the
the yard one day with with a captain
from the Bonanno crime family he was a
he lived in a cell across the hall from
me and he said to me how much time do
you have anyway and I said thirty months
and he said oh you could do that
standing on your head I said you know
what it feels like thirty years and he
said I'm gonna give you some advice
don't tell anybody that you have thirty
months because most of these guys are
here for 10 15 20 years and if they hear
that you're here for two and a half your
safety is gonna be in jeopardy so if
anybody asks you you tell them you have
five years and so that's what I did I
told everybody that I had five years and
then on the day of my release you know
the the the cops put up a sheet every
every day at four o'clock that lists the
next day's meetings and one day it said
Kiriakou R&D Bo's 700 that's receiving
and discharge and somebody son said are
you getting out tomorrow and I said why
because you're on the it's called a
call-out sheet you're on the call-out
sheet for our D I thought you had five
years I said yeah I have five years I'm
just mailing a package that's all okay
yes and I walked out it's just hard for
me to even understand how someone you're
so different like compared to you know
people I know I've talked to other
whistleblowers who have served time in
different capacities at least a couple
of them and you're such high character
and you served your country and you have
such high integrity and to being there
with like real criminals I mean that I'm
sure that was thank you and you know the
prison is fully a third
pedophiles and other child sex offenders
which made it even more difficult
because you just want to you just want
to kill every word I'm sure that's just
disgusting but you made it through and
and you know what let me interrupt you
for a second sure I made it I made it
through but not without some challenges
and I want to tell your listeners about
one challenge in particular because it's
a lesson for all of us right especially
especially in America of 2018 one of my
attorneys told me he said I'm gonna give
you a bit of advice that I know from
other clients who have had to go to
prison don't trust anybody and I mean
literally anybody
he said the FBI is upset that you got
off so easily they really wanted you to
go to prison for 45 years so don't trust
anybody they do this to organized crime
guys all the time they're upset because
these organized crime guys have short
sentences and they set them up while
they're in prison and I said ok and I
filed that in the back of my head so I
had been in prison about six weeks and a
guy who lived in my housing unit he was
an Afghan American he was a pharmacist
who had a bad oxycontin problem and was
doing eight years and very very nice guy
lovely guy he just happened to have a
drug problem and he belongs in rehab not
in prison but anyway he came up to me
and he said hey John there's a new guy
here that wants to meet you and I said
yeah who's that
and he said he's the former spokesman
for the Taliban and I said the former
spokesman for the Taliban you know what
I remember that case it was from like
2003 he was in on a gun charge but he
had been the Taliban spokesman inside
the United States and they got him on a
Terrorism conspiracy and a gun charge
and I said no thanks I don't want to I
don't want to talk to him I don't want
to meet him he said okay I'll tell him
well a few days later I'm out on the
yard just walking the track by myself
and this very obviously Afghan looking
man with a long
she beard walks up to meet with his hand
outstretched to shake my hand I put both
of my hands in the air because I
immediately assumed that either the cops
or the FBI were in the woods with their
long distance cameras to take a picture
of me embracing this convicted
terrorists so I put my hands up in the
air and I said back off and he said oh
come on man
we have a lot in common I said we have
nothing in common
I spent my career trying to kill people
like you oh no don't be like that he
said and I said look I'm not gonna be
able to say it in any more clear
language believe me alone come on let's
just talk I said leave me alone before I
do something that both of us are going
to regret and so we walked away well the
the main point of this story is this guy
had been in in my prison for three days
and two days later he was released so
why in the world would this guy have
been in my prison for five days on a
conspiracy to commit terrorism with a
gun charge because he was planted there
by the FBI to entrap me and that's what
the FBI does wow they really had it out
for you it really really did you had
Colleen on your show earlier correct
Colleen really gave me some great great
advice I relied on Colleen and on other
colleagues of Colleen's to just make
sure that I was pointed in the right
direction whenever whenever I had a
question about tactics like the story I
just told you I knew I could rely on
Colleen and she would give it to me
straight yeah she's a straight shooter
she's the best interview so so you spent
your time there and you you know you
wrote a book and then you're out and how
did that go I don't want to go to too
much personal life without your
permission
oh no you had to I know you had to get
back into the world and readjust what
did you do when you were released well
you know most people when they're
released from prison they think they can
just step back into their lives again
and everything
is gonna be fine and that's just not
true it's far far more stressful when
you first get out because you're
assigned to a halfway house now I didn't
have to spend any time in the halfway
house I checked in I was there nine
hours and they sent me home so I was
under house arrest for the next 87 days
but house arrest is very difficult
because it means that you literally
cannot leave the four walls of that
house
you can't walk to the curb to pick up
your paper you can't go sit on the deck
in the backyard you are inside the house
for the next 87 days and the halfway
house calls you constantly during the
day and by god you better pick up the
phone because if you don't then two cops
are coming to the house to get you and
take you back to prison in the mean time
the only time you are allowed to leave
the house is to go to the halfway house
to be drug tested to be harassed you
have to promise that you're looking for
a job and you have to outline all the
different jobs that you're looking for
well that's ownerís in and of itself and
I'll tell you another thing too they
have these mandatory classes at the
halfway houses there are 16 mandatory
classes and if you don't take them they
violate you and you go back to prison
but these classes are nonsensical for
somebody like me suicide prevention I
said don't you think you should have
given that class before I went to prison
I'm thrilled now that I'm home I don't
need the suicide prevention class now
it's kind of like closing the barn door
after the animals have already got now
another one was how to write a resume
thank you very much I know how to write
a resume how to conduct yourself in a
job interview again I appreciate the
thought but I don't need your help to
get through a job interview so I don't
know if it was anger rebellion arrogance
maybe I didn't sign up for a single one
of the classes and so I get a call one
day from the director of the halfway
house come in immediately so they
wouldn't allow me to drive the halfway
house is literally seven miles as the
crow flies from my house but it would
take me
two hours to get there because I have to
walk a mile to the subway take the
subway to Capitol Hill and then get on a
bus which takes me to literally the
worst neighborhood in the worst quadrant
of Washington get off the bus there and
walk another mile to the halfway house
so it was quite an ordeal so I got there
two hours later and everybody's there
the director and deputy director of the
halfway house a representative from the
Bureau of Prisons in Baltimore had
driven all the way to Washington my case
manager of the drug counselor and a
social worker and I go in and they all
have their angry faces on and the
director said we're discussing whether
or not to violate you I said okay you
haven't taken any of the mandatory
classes what do you have to say for
yourself
and I said and this is exactly how I
said it did you ever see that episode of
The Simpsons where Homer has to take a
parenting class and he goes a couple of
minutes late and when he walks in the
instructor is saying put a garbage can
lid on the garbage can people I can't
stress that enough is that what you're
gonna teach me in your mandatory classes
to put a garbage can lid on the garbage
can I said I don't need your stupid
mandatory classes it's a waste of my
time and of your time I would rather be
spending that time finding a job because
you people consistently harass me
because I haven't found a job well guess
what
it takes me two hours to get here two
hours to get home an hour that I have to
do your stupid drug tests and waste my
time talking to you that's five hours
that I could be out looking for a job
and they're all just looking at each
other step outside please
so I step outside so 45 minutes later
they call me back in they said okay
we've waived the classes and I said okay
and another thing I want permission to
drive I'm tired of taking the bus I'm
tired of wasting my day coming up here
all right you have permission to drive
and once I laid out those markers I was
okay
they knew that they couldn't push me
around because I
wasn't afraid of them you know just like
I told the warden one day and I put this
in my book too he was trying to threaten
me because I had been writing this blog
from prison and it was the blog that led
to the pen First Amendment award and he
wanted to put me in solitary he was
threatening me and I said warden with
all due respect I have gone nose-to-nose
with al-qaeda with Hezbollah with the
Iranians and I'm supposed to be afraid
of you and you're solitary I said please
you've never served in Yemen I can do
solitary standing on my fingertips and
then he backed off they always do
because if you show them that you know
the rule is better than they do and that
you know that you have not given up your
First Amendment right to freedom of
speech
they always back down sounds like it
well you put them in their place I tried
it was risky but I but I succeeded well
that's the important thing you know and
you do have to take a stand and we need
already been through so much as well and
it seemed to have worked out for you so
I guess there's a few things I wanted to
go into in delve into a little bit more
at some point and whatever or do you
care you choose but like I wanted to go
into the acts of terror or the acts of
torture and some of the laws surrounding
that and what that entails I'm very
interested in that and then you know
what you're planning on doing in the
future which work you have lined up and
then maybe going to whistleblowing in
general as well as I close out to kind
of give a space or to talk about what we
need to do to protect people like you so
this doesn't happen to them this is
unacceptable people I talk to a lot of
people and you people I don't know if
you know this people Revere you
surprised how many people know you and
they Revere you and your character yeah
they say only the kind of things about
you I think so much yeah I mean that was
my impression when I talked on the phone
a year ago you just sounded like such a
sweet wonderful man I think bill made he
somehow suggested you or mentioned you
or something those are giants oh he is
so what you know the reason why I do
what I do is because of him if I
interviewed him on a different podcast
at one point and he is a hero in talking
to him and Curly role model yes I mean
for Edward Snowden and and you know he
did what he did because of Bill Benny
was his hero and so speaking with those
two men changed the course of my life
you know all of a sudden I had this
interest in people like you and then
working with you know other people other
human rights activists and people who
are also you know being tortured or
being subjugated by the government in
different capacities so you know it was
very concerning to me so here I sit
because of those two men wonderful yeah
they're really delightful people so
anyways um yeah so I guess whatever what
do you want to you know approach those
questions sure well let's start with
with torture you know when I was first
approached it was kind of an odd
experience I was in the cafeteria at the
CIA I had just gotten back from Pakistan
and a senior officer of the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center came up to me
and he said hey welcome back I said yeah
thanks good to be back he said yeah I'm
glad I ran into you I wanted to ask you
do you want to be certified in the use
of enhanced interrogation techniques and
I had never heard that term before and I
said what's that mean and very excitedly
he said we're gonna get rough with these
guys and I said well what does that mean
and so he laid out these ten techniques
from what they called the attention
grasp all the way up to two
waterboarding and two techniques that I
always believed were worse than
waterboarding and I said oh that sounds
like a torture program can you oh he
said yeah sure no no it was sleep
deprivation and the cold sell and I'll
get into those in a second okay I said
that sounds like a torture program no no
he says we we got it approved by the
President and by the Justice Department
and I said yeah you may have but I said
listen just in my gut I have a moral and
ethical problem with this and he said
okay suit yourself
as it so happened
I was passed over for promotion a month
later now here I had just caught the
number three in al-qaeda and they passed
me over for promotion so I went into the
deputy director's office he I had worked
for him years earlier and I said what do
you mean passed over for promotion what
do I have to catch bin Laden to get
promoted around here and he said well we
talked about you in the promotion panel
and you didn't want to be trained in the
in the enhanced interrogation techniques
and his exact words that displayed a
shocking lack of commitment to
counterterrorism well the station chief
in Pakistan for whom I had worked had
been promoted to be the associate deputy
director of the whole CIA and he made me
his executive assistant and he promoted
me so I got the promotion but I realized
I'm on the other side of this thing and
it's kind of lonely over here but I
thought you know I grew up in um I grew
up in a very progressive household my
parents were you know followers of the
news I remember when I was six years old
and I remember this very vividly and
I've talked to Daniel Ellsberg about
this but when I was six Dan released the
Pentagon Papers and of course it was
major national news and even as a
six-year-old I remember my parents
talking about it at the dinner table
because we always talked about the
events of the day at the dinner table
and in our house Daniel Ellsberg was a
hero he was a hero
he was somebody to be emulated and so
from when I was a kid I was never really
afraid to stand alone because if I
really believed in my heart that I was
right then that's all that really
mattered and so I stuck it out and I
refused to be trained so you know these
techniques some of them clearly were not
torture if I grabbed you by the lapels
and I say answer my question doggone you
that's not torture but they very quickly
progressed into torture for example one
of them was called walling
wal Li ng and that is when a prisoner
has his hands tied behind his back a
towel is wrapped around his neck to
prevent whiplash and then he slammed
into a wall now the wall has to be
fiberboard or something akin to
fiberboard because you don't want to
cause permanent damage and that towel is
supposed to cushion the blow so Abu
Zubaydah was was a victim of walling but
they didn't wrap his neck in the towel
and the wall was made of concrete
now there's another prisoner I don't
know if I should say his name or not I
won't just to be on the safe side right
who was walled repeatedly to the point
where he has permanent brain damage and
is unable to participate in his own
defense so how is that legal
the other two techniques that I told you
I had particular objections to besides
waterboarding which everybody knows
about were sleep deprivation and the
cold cell
now sleep deprivation sounds like no big
deal and in 2002
the Secretary of Defense at the time
Donald Rumsfeld famously said that he
didn't believe that there really was
such a thing as sleep deprivation
because he can go 48 hours without
stopping you know his work and his desk
is a stand-up desk he doesn't even have
a chair and so he doesn't believe that
my sleep deprivation is a problem well
we can see what he's asked exactly the
point we know from the from the American
Psychological Association that people
begin to lose their minds at day 7 with
no sleep they begin to die around day 9
well the CIA was authorized to keep
people awake for 12 days so how is that
legal and moral and ethical the other
one is the cold sell the cold sell is
very simple a prisoner is stripped naked
he's chained to an eyebolt in the
ceiling so that he can't sit or lay or
get comfortable in any way his cell is
chilled to 50 degrees Fahrenheit and
every hour a CIA officer goes into the
cell and throws a bucket of ice water on
him we we killed people with that
technique we killed them
now I understand actually like
intellectually I understand when
President Obama said we need to look
forward not backward I get it if you're
a CIA officer and you've been told that
you're operating within the confines of
the law and you do what you're told to
do I understand but no one was
authorized to murder prisoners nobody
and there was never any justice for
those people that we killed
what about I'd heard another person tell
me that they would have them like
masturbate and do in hold really
uncomfortable poses is that true or is
that something you were aware of um I
have never heard that at least not in
the CIA context now I I'm not an expert
on what happened at Abu Ghraib which was
a military torture program a rogue
torture program that would not surprise
me at all if you told me that it
happened at Abu Ghraib yeah
so yes I'm just curious if that was
something that was across the board or
like you said a rogue group would have
Tyrone yeah and there were other things
that CIA officers did especially to Abu
Zubaydah that had been outlined in the
Senate torture report that were never
authorized and certainly never
prosecuted we knew for example that Abu
Zubaydah had an irrational fear of
insects and so they put him in a in a
box like a coffin and then they poured a
container of cockroaches in on top of
him and then closed the coffin and just
listen to him scream how is that legal
and moral and ethical it can't be it's
repulsive Bakshi I don't even know what
they come up with these things it is it
does come up with use I'm just curious I
know it's a neat
I've talked to enough people in
government to know it's always need to
know and you don't get your information
but I'm very curious who sets the
standards or who sets these policies
these all came out of the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center yep
now they didn't invent them you know
Chinese Communists used them the
Belgians used them in the Congo a
hundred and twenty years ago the Chinese
used them back in the in the fourteen
and fifteen hundreds these are old
techniques but they were used because
they work right you know and this is
another issue to hide abate a lot of
people in public venues whether they're
at universities or radio or television
shows I debate people who are pro they
want they wouldn't call themselves Pro
torture but certainly Pro enhanced
interrogation techniques and their
argument is that is that these
techniques worked well first of all
that's not the issue it doesn't matter
if they work and first of all what does
work mean it got somebody to talk lots
of things can get people to talk raping
them gets them to talk you gonna rape
them I mean we don't because it's it's
it's an abomination but if you if you
want to get them to talk killing their
children in front of them would work are
you gonna do that next raping their
wives in front of them you know that
that might work so it's not an issue of
whether it works I'm gonna sound like a
broken record it's an issue of whether
or not it's moral legal and ethical
right but that's not the argument that
the government wants to hear when do you
think this is all this all came out of
9/11 these type of all of it yeah the
problems the Patriot Act just caused
just to the Patriot problem warrantless
wiretapping mass surveillance all of
these were byproducts of 9/11 which
makes me conclude that here we are all
these years later and Osama bin Laden
one you know he wanted to effect
American society he wanted to crash the
economy and affect society and he
crashed the economy he put us into a
permanent wartime economy he
this into a period where we spend untold
trillions of dollars on national defense
we've lost our civil rights and civil
liberties we have a Patriot Act we have
secret FISA courts so bin Laden one
that's unfortunate so what do you think
is gonna have to happen is there
anything kind of moving ahead to kind of
protect human beings from being tortured
I mean I know they're working on the
surveillant aspects although I don't
know it doesn't walk a win situation at
all not yet yeah on torture we've had a
couple of positive forward progress
first of all Barack Obama signed an
executive order his very first week as
president banning the enhanced
interrogation techniques that's all fine
and good an executive order has the the
force of law but it can be changed by
the stroke of the pen from the next
president so it was a temporary measure
a temporary halt but in the summer of
Congress passed the McCain fine Stein
amendment to the National Defense
Authorization Act it also has the force
of law it was passed into law and it
limits the techniques that can be used
to those techniques outlined in the Army
Field Manual that's great but what's to
keep a hawkish president from just
changing the Army Field Manual right you
know another important point to Ella to
make is that we already have laws on the
books that govern these kinds of things
we have the federal torture Act of 1946
which specifically banned exactly these
techniques that you and I have just been
talking about in 1946 we executed
Japanese soldiers who had waterboarded
American prisoners of war right
that was a death-penalty offense because
it was considered torture in January
1968 The Washington Post ran a
front-page photograph of an American
soldier waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner the day that that picture was
published the Secretary of Defense
Robert McNamara ordered an investigation
the soldier was arrested he was charged
with torture convicted and sentenced to
20 years in prison
well why was torture illegal in 2040 I'm
sorry in 1946 and illegal in 1968 but
somehow not illegal in 2002 or 2015 the
law never changed
we changed we changed as a people as a
nation and shame on us so we need to get
back to our roots we need to get back to
a rule of law yes
9/11 was traumatic believe me I was in
the building at the time like everybody
else in the building I volunteered to go
to Afghanistan or Pakistan and to do
whatever my country needed for me to do
but my god we can't lose the sense of
who we are as people
right we're supposed to be the good guys
yes and the way things are the way
things have been going for the past
decade or so it doesn't seem indicate
above that at all
so not at all so what's your plan what
do you have next what are you gonna be
doing next with your life and are you
used to work on the horizon or what
projects yeah I've got a couple of
things going I have a daily two-hour
radio show here in the Washington area
yeah 105.5 FM and 1390 a.m. so it's on
from 4:00 to 6:00 p.m. and it's a news
show we have guests and talk about all
the issues of the day
which is a lot of fun it's a good fit
for me and I have a weekly syndicated
column with reader supported news that
keeps keeps me busy too I'm working on
my fourth book right now you know I made
such good friends in the Mafia
[Laughter]
and then you know even before I got in
trouble I as a hobby I like to write
television pilots that's I've sold seven
over the years and I came up with an
idea when I was in prison that I thought
was my best idea ever and I sold it to
MGM and to make a long story short
they've ordered a pilot and it's the
first time I've ever made it to pilot
and so I'm gonna go to Los Angeles we
just finished the fifth draft of our
script I'm gonna go to Los Angeles in a
couple of weeks and we're gonna pitch it
to networks and hope for the best
yeah that's funny because I did get a
question from Kate Ryan I believe you
know Kate Ryan she's a dear yes I sure
do wonderful just a decent human being
and she wanted me to ask you about the
TV series that you plan on doing with
Oliver Stone's yeah yeah so Oliver as
soon as I got home Oliver called me and
said let's do something together I said
I'd love to so I went out to Los Angeles
I have great representatives out there a
terrific agent and I love my
entertainment lawyer and they're really
great and so Oliver and I went to the
History Channel and the History Channel
optioned it's funny they optioned one
chapter from my first book and they
wanted to do this series based just on
that chapter and it was about life
inside the CIA immediately before during
and after 9/11 and how this how this
organization of thousands of smart
patriotic people went from being smart
patriotic people and then six months
later ended up with a secret prison
system a torture program and
extraordinary renditions and so we
developed this series together and and
made it to the end and then the History
Channel cancelled it they said it was it
was too expensive to produce and that's
okay you know that kind of thing happens
like I say I've sold seven and on this
this other one I finally made it to
pilot okay well that's good to hear
great to hear and then I haven't
couple of the question I guess she was
gonna ask them of John whiteheads
friends but I'm not sure let's see what
the questions oh I want to ask you about
Geoff sterling I've been working with
Holly we've had some scary things happen
I don't know if you would I think you
already at that point I was just
disgusted to her she was called me Kate
put me in touch with her and we were
really concerned about her husband he
was having heart issues and that where
he was at and I just was very concerned
she did say he did kind of get some help
and I just really did to my best I could
with people I know to ruffle some
feathers but there's another it's just
as I feel I feel for her I like her so
much I like him so much and I haven't
had to haven't spoken to him but you
know I speak to Holly and so yes I don't
know what's gonna happen out of that
right I'm not sure I wish her thoughts
on that well Jeffrey's still in the
halfway house and right they're making
they're making his stay there very
difficult um they won't let him have a
telephone because bo P regulations are
such that you're not allowed to have a
cell phone if it has a camera and if it
has internet well every cell phone has a
camera and internet so in every halfway
house but Jefferies you have to white
out the camera and just promise them
that you won't surf the internet and if
they want to check your phone they have
the right to check it with with Jeffery
just because they're they're actively
trying to be as difficult as they can
with him because they don't like him
they just won't let him have a phone and
so it's hard for him to stay in touch
with Holly
at the same time Jeffery is like me in
that he doesn't need to learn how to
write a resume the guy's an attorney and
a decorated fraud investigators exactly
so he doesn't need their stupid classes
they're forcing him to go through the
classes and instead of just sending him
directly home to home confinement just
to harass him they've kept him at the
halfway house so they've told Holly that
he's not even eligible to go home until
this coming Thursday
um Holly purposely has not gone to the
press because she doesn't want to ruffle
the the Bureau of Prisons feathers and
and we have to wait and see until
Thursday to see if he comes home if he
doesn't come home I told her that I was
gonna write about it again I'm in very
close touch with them and so you know I
want to I don't want to make things
difficult for him at the same time we
just can't abide this kind of behavior
from the Bureau of Prisons it's
discriminatory I could give maybe people
you can maybe you probably can word it a
little bit better give a little history
about mr. sterling what happened to him
yeah Jeffrey sterling is a bonafide
whistleblower he was a CIA officer in
the agency's Iran operations division
he's also African American which is very
important in the story so Jeffrey was
involved in an operation that he
believed constituted waste fraud abuse
or illegality which is the definition of
whistleblowing
he went to his superiors they told him
to mind his own business
and and so he complained up the chain of
command which is exactly what you're
supposed to do when he didn't get any
satisfaction there he went to the
Congressional Oversight Committee which
is also exactly what you're supposed to
do and so as punishment for going to
Congress with his concerns
he had a an assignment rescinded he was
supposed to go to the Middle East and
they yanked the assignment out from
under him and when he asked why his
supervisor said well we thought it would
be funny if you know not funny ha-ha but
funny odd for a big black guy to be
speaking persian farsi and jeffrey
responded when did you realize i was
black and so they said well we're gonna
send you to germany with his his things
had already been shipped out to the
Middle East so he said I don't want to
go
Germany I was told I was going to the
Middle East well how about we just fire
you and they fired it so he filed a
racial discrimination suit which believe
me enraged them the thing is is the
CIA's long been guilty of racial
discrimination and sex discrimination it
was only in the nineteen nineties that
that women were were given equality to
men in the CIA at least in the
operational division so I've had some
conversations about that so she
validates exactly that statement oh it's
just dreadful in fact there was a
class-action suit of female officers
that was settled in 1993 and in the
settlement that in the decision the
judge said he had never seen a case
where the defendant had so fully
documented the charges against itself as
the CIA had done right crazy so Jeffrey
was fired he filed a racial
discrimination suit well James Rison of
the New York Times covered that story
and so Jeffrey and rised and spoke as it
turns out 52 separate times never for
more than a couple of minutes at the
same time Rison wrote a book called Bush
at war which talked about this Iran
operation that constituted waste fraud
abuse or illegality now there was
someone on Capitol Hill on the Senate
Intelligence Committee who was thought
to have been the source rise and source
for that story the CIA of course pointed
the finger right at Jeffrey and they
said you're a malcontent you complained
about this program you're talking to
Rison your Rison source jeffrey said i'm
not rising source I have been talking to
Rison it's been about my sex my racial
discrimination suit which he has covered
in the New York Times well the Justice
Department decided there's no sense in
going after this guy on Capitol Hill
when we already have this guy Jeffrey
sterling we're gonna go after him they
repeatedly offered Jeffrey deals
to plead guilty just take the deal and
he refused he refused for a total of 11
years right not 11 I guess - to nine
years and the reason he refused to take
the deal was because he was innocent
yeah and he told me he said you know I I
thought as soon as I got in front of a
jury they would realize how ridiculous
this was well remember I said in the
beginning of our conversation the
Eastern District of Virginia look at how
your jury is made up they would convict
a bologna sandwich if the government
asked them to and so Jeffrey was
convicted on nine felony counts
including seven counts of espionage the
only thing that saved him from dying in
prison was just serendipitously his
sentencing date came the day after David
Petraeus his sentencing date and so
judge brinkema even though she's a
hanging judge she was my judge she was
Jeffrey's judge and she already assigned
to herself the Ed Snowden case she said
in good conscience she couldn't give him
what she had wanted to give him because
of what to tray us had done you got a
sweetheart deal we're running out of
time here but I want you to go ahead and
say one more time what you're doing and
I'll discuss Jeffrey next week as well
so can you give what it is you're doing
you're sure yes I have a radio on 105.5
have founded the Washington area from
4:00 to 6:00 in the afternoon by day
through Friday and a weekly column at
reader supported news org in your book
my book is doing time like a spy how the
CIA taught me to survive and thrive in
prison well thank you John so much I
appreciate it
you